norwichunion.com 2019-12-19

# Privacy Policy - Aviva

**What “we” means** This privacy policy is issued on behalf of the Aviva Group companies within the United Kingdom. When we mention "Aviva", "we", "us" or "our", what we mean is the relevant company in the Aviva Group that  **processes**  your  **personal information**.

**We have separate privacy notices for our products**

If you’re one of our customers, we will give you separate privacy notices when we ask for your  **personal information** , for example, when you get a quote or apply for our products. Read them carefully, as they’ll tell you which Aviva company is responsible for managing your  **personal information**  and provide more details about how we’ll use it in relation to that product.

You’ll find more privacy notices when you use our apps and platforms such as Drive or MyAviva. This Policy supplements – but doesn’t override – them.

We’ll keep this Policy up to date with the latest legal requirements, so please check back here for the current version.

**Sensitive information**

Sometimes we’ll ask about your  **health,**  details of  **offences and convictions**  or other sensitive information about the person(s) who is/are being insured and their family members. We know how sensitive that data is, so protecting it is a top priority.

**Payment information**

If you buy a product directly from our website or other Aviva sales channel, we’ll ask for  **payment information**. We need this to complete your purchase. __

**Marketing and customer insights**

We carry out customer insight analysis from our interactions with you to help improve our products and services, and keep you informed about offerings that may be of interest to you.    

**Information about other individuals**

Most of the information we collect relates to the person taking out a product (or persons where it’s taken out jointly). We may also ask for information about other individuals if we need it. Examples include:

  * if you ask us to provide insurance for other household or family members, or members of a group
  * if we ask an  **insured person**  to provide  **health information**  about other family members where this is relevant to the risk we’re covering when we  **arrange**  a policy
  * if we need information about other individuals when we handle a  **claim** , such as injured third parties

If you provide us with information about someone else, we’ll assume that you have their permission. We’ll  **process**  their  **personal information**  according to this Privacy Policy so please encourage them to read it if they want to find out more.

**Brokers, intermediaries, employers and third parties**

Many customers buy our products through an insurance  **broker,  **financial adviser or one of our  **business partners.  **We also receive  **personal information**  from other third parties, including attorneys, trustees and family members. It is their responsibility to make sure they explain to the person whose information is being shared that they are doing so, and ask for permission if needed.  **Who we share personal information with**

Depending on the product or service, we’ll share  **personal information**  with a number of our trusted third parties, including:

  * financial advisers and **  business partners** who help us  **arrange**  our products
  * **insurers,  **reinsurers and  **brokers**  who help us  **manage**  and  **underwrite**  our products and provide reinsurance and insurance services
  * **data analysts**  and providers of data services who support us with developing our products and prices
  * comparison websites and similar companies that offer ways to research and apply for financial services products
  * regulators who regulate how we operate, these include the  **FCA** ,  **PRA** , **  Financial Ombudsman**,  **HMRC** , **  The Pensions Regulator** and  **ICO**
  * **solicitors**  and professional service firms who act on our or your behalf, or who represent a  **third-party claimant**
  * **third-party administrators**  who help us  **manage**  our products and services
  * **loss adjusters**  and  **claims experts**  who help us  **handle claims**
  * **assistance providers**  who can help provide you with assistance in the event of a  **claim**
  * **service providers**  who help operate our IT and back office systems, including our underwriting processes
  * medical professionals, if we need to access health records or assessments for the purposes of  **arranging**  and  **underwriting  **certain products or facilitating and  **handling claims**
  * third-party case  **manage** rs, handling your care or treatment pathway
  * employers and third parties that provide services to you and your employer in respect of a pension scheme, including pension planning services for employees
  * **media agencies**  and other providers of marketing and display advertising services, who help us make sure you receive marketing content that’s relevant to you and your preferences

**Extraordinary circumstances**

Occasionally and only where necessary to fulfil our legal obligations, conduct investigations and/or deliver our services, we may share your information with private investigators, police, courts, external auditors, accountants,  **DWP  **or other IT  **service providers**  – eg tracing services, medical underwriting, and pension transfers. We also work with anti-fraud and credit reference agencies to help us detect and prevent fraud and  **manage**  credit risk.

Motor and home insurance

When you take out a motor or home policy, we’ll collect and use your  **personal information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite  **and **  manage **your policy, as well as prevent fraud and  **handle claims.**

The  **personal information  **we use for these types of policies includes any relevant **  offences and convictions **for each person to be insured under the policy as well as any relevant  **health information** , for example if a  **claim**  is made involving a personal injury.

If you take out a motor policy we’ll also collect and use information about you and your vehicle. We’ll get this information from you, public registers, our trusted third parties such as the  **MIB  **and from information already held by us, eg from previous policies or quotes. If you’re seeking a policy with telematics capability, we’ll also use  **telematics data.**

Your driving history

We may ask you to provide the driving licence number so we can quickly get useful data from the DVLA such as the licence status of each driver, their licence entitlement, relevant restriction information, endorsement and conviction details. If you do not wish to provide us with your licence information, you can choose to answer the questions about your licence information yourself. 

We’ll also add details of the policy to the Motor Insurance Database maintained by the  **MIB**. The  **MIB**  may make this information available to authorised bodies such as the  **DVLA** ,  **DVLNI**  and  **IFB**.

About your home

When you take out a home policy, we may obtain information about you and your home from publicly available registers and databases. These may include land registers, as well as information already held by us, such as information about previous policies or  **claims** , or from our trusted third parties, such as commercially available property databases where this will help us  **underwrite**  the policy.

In some cases when you apply for motor or home insurance, we may share your information with credit reference agencies so they can carry out searches relating to you.

Automated decision making

We need your  **personal information**  when you apply for a policy to decide if we can offer a policy and, if so, on what terms. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided including address, post code, and age, (and, for motor policies, we use marital status, employment details and details of health and relevant  **offences and convictions**  for you and any other drivers). The automated engine may also validate information you provide against other records we hold about you in our systems and third party databases, including public databases. We may supplement the information you provide with information from third parties who can provide more information about your vehicle or property (including  **DVLA**  databases, land registries and commercially available property databases). 

Throughout the term of these types of policies we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy, such as offering renewal or dealing with  **claims**. We may use the information to perform analytics and ensure we’re appropriately pricing our products. 

Verifying claims

If a  **claim**  is made, we use your  **personal information**  to verify the  **claim**  and ensure that we pay out to the right person. In addition we’ll need to collect and use the following  **personal information** :

  * for a  **claim**  following a motor accident, we’ll ask for details of the  **claim** , information about those involved and any personal injury you or others may have suffered
  * for a  **claim**  under a home policy, we’ll ask you to confirm your identity and provide details of the  **claim**.

Travel and health insurance

Where you take out a travel or health policy we’ll collect and use your  **personal information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite  **and **  manage **your policy, as well as prevent fraud and  **handle claims.**

The  **personal information**  we use for these types of policies includes  **health information**  for each person to be insured, for example other family members who are to be covered under the insurance policy.

For health policies we may also ask you to authorise your healthcare provider to supply relevant supporting information, including, where relevant,  **health information**  about the family or personal history of each person to be insured.

Automated decision making

We need your  **personal information**  when you apply to us to decide if we can offer a policy and, if so, on what terms. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided (including address, age and any medical conditions of the policyholder and any other people to be insured). The automated engine may also validate information you provide against other records we hold about you in our systems and third party databases, including public databases.

Throughout the life of these types of policies, we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy such as offering renewal or dealing with claims. We may also use the  **personal information**  to perform analytics and ensure that our products are appropriately priced.

Verifying claims

If a  **claim**  is made, we use  **personal information**  to verify the  **claim**  and ensure that we pay out to the right person. In addition, we’ll need to collect and use the following  **personal information** :

  * for  **claims**  under a travel policy we’ll need to ask you to confirm your identity and provide details of the  **claim** , including information about any illness or personal injury suffered. We’ll share information with  **assistance providers**  where necessary to help deal with a  **claim.**

for  **claims**  under a health policy we’ll ask you to confirm the identity of the person making the  **claim**  and provide details of the health condition to which the  **claim**  relates. To assist with your claim we may also ask you to authorise your healthcare provider to supply information. We may also pass information you have given us to your treating healthcare provider or case  **manage** r.

**Pet, mobile/gadget and personal accident insurance  **

When you take out a pet, mobile/gadget or personal accident policy we’ll collect and use your  **personal manage information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite**  and your policy, as well as prevent fraud and  **handle claims**.

The  **personal information**  we use for these types of policies include:

  * For pet – information about your pet including name, gender, date of birth, medical conditions, if your pet has been chipped/tagged and/or neutered, if your pet has been involved in any incidents or accidents that may give rise to legal action against you
  * For mobile/gadget – information about the type of your gadget, its make, model, value, date of purchase and serial number or IMEI number
  * For personal accident - your age and the level of cover you choose

We need your  **personal information**  when you apply to us to decide if we can offer a policy and, if so, on what terms. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that process, which takes account of the information you have provided, which includes the information listed above.

Throughout the life of these types of policies, we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy, such as allowing you to exercise any cover change options you have under the policy, offering renewal, where applicable, and dealing with claims.

**Verifying claims**

If a  **claim**  is made, we use  **personal information**  to verify the  **claim**  and ensure that we pay out to the right person. This will differ, depending on the type of policy:

  * For pet insurance claims we’ll also collect information about any illness or injury in relation to the pet and we may also seek information from the treating vet. Where a  **claim**  arises because a pet has caused damage or personal injury to another person we’ll also need to collect information in relation to this
  * For mobile/gadget claims we’ll need to verify your identity and collect details of the circumstances of the  **claim**  and the IMEI number of the mobile device
  * For personal accident policies we’ll need to verify your identity and collect details of the accident or injury leading to the  **claim**. We may also need to ask you to authorise your healthcare provider to provide information to assist in assessing the  **claim**.

Life insurance

Where you take out life insurance with us (for example, life, critical illness or income protection policy), we’ll collect and use your  **personal information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite**  and  **manage**  your policy, as well as prevent fraud and  **handle claims**.

Except for certain types of life insurance which are not  **underwritten**  for example, over 50s life insurance and free parent life cover, the  **personal information**  we use includes  **health information, lifestyle information**  and  **employment status  **(including, for income protection only, level of earnings) of each  **insured person**. We’ll also collect the family or personal history of the  **insured person** , or details of appointed  **trustees**  where policies are placed under trust.

Automated decision making

We need your  **personal information**  when you apply to us to decide if we can offer a policy and, if so, on what terms. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided (including your age, whether you smoke, your answers to our health and lifestyle questions, including your family medical history) along with the amount of cover you wish to obtain. We’ll make clear to you in the application for each policy whether automated underwriting is used.

Where we collect and use  **health information** , we may ask each  **insured person**  to authorise a healthcare provider to supply relevant supporting information, including, where relevant,  **health information**  about their family or personal history

Throughout the life of these types of policies, we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy, such as allowing you to exercise any options you may have under the policy. We may also use the information (including  **health information** ) to perform analytics and ensure that our products are appropriately priced.

Verifying claims

If a  **claim**  is made, we use your  **personal information**  to verify the  **claim**  and ensure that we pay out to the right person. This will differ, depending on the type of policy:

  * For claims under a life insurance policy, we’ll need to ask you to confirm your identity, provide details of the policyholder and (if different) the  **insured person** , including details of their death so that we can assess the  **claim**
  * For claims under a critical illness or income protection policy, we’ll need to ask you to confirm your identity and provide details of your health condition. We may also ask you to authorise your healthcare provider to provide information to assist in assessing the  **claim**

Equity release

Where you take out an equity release lifetime mortgage product we’ll collect and use your  **personal information**  to decide if we can offer you a product and, if so, on what terms. We’ll also use it to  **arrange**  and  **manage**  your account, as well as prevent fraud.

The  **personal information**  we use for this type of product may include how long you have lived at the property, the estimated property value, the purpose of the loan, the ownership status of your home and what proportion is owned by you as well as information about your legal adviser and existing lender.

If you select certain features of the product, we’ll also collect  **health information**  to assess risk and eligibility for the product. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided (including your age, whether you smoke and your answers to our health and lifestyle questions). We’ll collect information about you and any person to be a joint account holder as well as any occupants of the property.

Throughout the duration of your product we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the product for example to provide you with information and  **process**  payments.

Annuities

Where you take out an annuity policy we’ll collect and use your  **personal**   **information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite**  and  **manage  **your policy and prevent fraud.

The  **personal information**  we use for these types of products includes  **health information** and  **lifestyle information**  about you and anyone else to be insured under the policy. We use this information to decide whether, and on what terms, we can offer you a policy. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided (including your age, whether you smoke and your answers to our health and lifestyle questions).

Occupational pension schemes

**Trustees**  of an occupational pension scheme may take out an annuity policy for the purposes of the scheme. Where they do this we may collect  **personal information**  about members of the scheme to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite**  and  **manage**  the policy, as well as prevent fraud.  ****

Throughout the life of these types of product, we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy, for example, to pay benefits.

Pensions, savings and investments

Where you take out a pension, savings or investment product we’ll collect and use your  **personal**   **information**  to  **arrange**  and  **manage  **your policy, as well as prevent fraud.

We may also collect and use your  **personal information**  for these purposes if you:

  * join your employer’s pension scheme and they use an Aviva pension product for their scheme
  * are a member of your employer’s pension scheme and the  **trustees**  of the scheme use an Aviva investment product for the purposes of the scheme

The  **personal information**  we use for these types of products may include your:

  * **employment status**
  * details and value of your pension
  * salary details
  * marital status
  * tax information
  * national insurance number

Throughout the life of these types of product, we’ll hold your  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the product, for example to  **process**  investment instructions and withdrawals from your product. 

Business insurance including motor and non-motor business insurance and corporate specialty risks

Where you take out a business insurance policy with us we may collect and use  **personal information**  to  **arrange** ,  **underwrite** ,  **manage**  your policy, prevent fraud and  **handle claims**.

The  **personal information**  we use for these types of policies may include information about your business, including the business name, the contact person for your business, details of directors, partners or individual traders for the business and  **payment information**.

We may also collect details about the number of employees, details of employees (including any  **offences and convictions**  that we need to know about to allow us to underwrite the policy), their role in the company and details of the business assets or liabilities to be insured.

For business health, life, travel and personal accident insurance

The information we collect may include  **health Information**  for each person to be insured, for example employees who are to be covered under the insurance policy. We may also ask you to authorise your healthcare provider to supply relevant supporting information, including, where relevant,  **health information**  about the family or personal history of each person to be insured. We need this information to  **underwrite**  and  **manage**  the policy and facilitate and  **handle claims**.

For business motor insurance

We’ll collect  **identity information**  in relation to employees or other people to be insured under the policy. Information may include any relevant  **offences and convictions**  or  **health information**  for drivers to be insured under the policy. We also collect and use information about drivers and vehicles to be insured from public registers, from our trusted third parties, such as the  **MIB,**  and information already held by Aviva, eg from previous policies or quotes.

If you’re seeking a policy with telematics capability, we’ll also use  **telematics data**. We’ll also add details of the policy to the Motor Insurance Database maintained by the  **MIB**. The  **MIB**  may make this information available to authorised bodies such as the  **DVLA** ,  **DVLNI**  and  **IFB**.

Automated decision making

We need the  **personal information**  when you apply to us to decide if we can offer a policy and, if so, on what terms. We use an automated underwriting engine as part of that  **process** , which takes account of the information you have provided (including  **health information**  or  **offences and convictions**  data, where appropriate). The automated engine may also validate information you provide against other records we hold in our systems and third party databases, including public databases. We may supplement the information you provide with information from third parties who can provide more information about the vehicles or property to be insured.

Throughout the life of these types of policies we’ll hold the  **personal information**  to enable us to properly administer the policy, for example to offer renewal, make mid-term changes you request and deal with  **claims**. We may use the  **personal information**  to perform analytics and ensure that our products are appropriately priced.

Verifying claims

If a  **claim**  is made, we use the  **personal information**  to verify the identity of the policyholder and (if different) provide details of the insured, so that we can identify them. We’ll also need you to provide details of the  **claim**  so that we can assess the  **claim**. Where necessary, this will include providing details of any accidents or personal injuries that have been suffered as part of the  **claim** , either by an  **insured person**  or third party. In certain circumstances (for example where personal liability is covered) it may be necessary to collect details of alleged offences in relation to an  **insured person**.

Preventing fraud

We’ll also use your  **personal information**  to detect and prevent fraudulent practices, fight  **financial crime**  and meet our regulatory responsibilities.

If you’re making a  **claim** , we may use  **profiling**  and other forms of automated processing to assess if your  **claim**  may be fraudulent. This assessment may involve the use of your  **sensitive personal information**. For example, we may use your past motoring convictions for motoring insurance.
